A Finding Aid to the Timothy Casper Papers, 1943-1981, bulk 1950-1969, in the Archives of American Art.
Archives of American Art
Timothy Casper papers
1943-1981
bulk 1950-1969
Archives of American Art
Casper, Timothy F., 1943-1964
Casper, Elise Ott
AAA.casptim
Archival Resource Key
3.4 Linear feet
The papers of Timothy Casper measure 3.4 linear feet and date from 1943-1981, with bulk dates from 1950-1969. The papers document Casper's career and life which was cut short when he died from a car crash at age twenty-one. Included are biographical material; correspondence between Casper and his mother Elise Casper Ott, and from Elise to others regarding Timothy's artistsic legacy; writings; exhibition files; personal business records; printed material; photographic material and artwork.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Scope and Contents
The papers of Timothy Casper measure 3.4 linear feet and date from 1943-1981, with bulk dates from 1950-1969. The papers document Casper's career and life which was cut short when he died from a car crash at age twenty-one. Included are biographical material; correspondence; writings; exhibition files; personal business records; printed material; photographic material and artwork. Biographical material includes Casper's birth and baptism certificates, his social security card, materials related to Casper's education and resumes and biographic summaries. Correspondence contains letters from Timothy Casper to his mother Elise Ott Casper, and from Elise to others regarding Timothy's artistsic legacy. Writing by Timothy Casper include a diary, an eight grade essay on monoprinting, travel notes and a draft of an New York University course schedule. Writings by others include teacher feedback notes, an annotated list of Casper's artwork, writings related to the planning and publishing of a book on Timothy Casper including a introduction outline, lists of artworks to be featured and correspondence. Exhibition files document six memorial exhibitions of Casper's work. Items include guest and address lists, agendas, writings, invoices, artwork insurance policies, correspondence and printed material. Personal business records include Timothy Casper's estate papers and life insurance documentation, alphabetized artwork title cards with corresponding loan and sale information and an invoice for napkins from Casper's printing business "Casper Studios". Printed Material includes exhibition flyers and newspaper clippings, primarily related to Casper's memorial exhibitions; a copy of Timothy F. Casper 1943-1964 a retrospective book on the life and career of Casper; a program for an elementary school play Casper participated in; brochures for different museums; New York University Graduate School bulletin publications; postcards from different locations in Washington D.C and miscellanea. Photographic material contains portraits of Timothy Casper as a child as well as photographs of his artwork. Also found are three family photo albums of the Caspers, their family and various places they visited, along with a photo album of Casper attending Woodcraft summer camp. Artwork consists of seven sketchbooks, loose and matted sketches, paintings, etching and linocut prints, a woven basket and bracelets. Also found is an extensive amount of Timothy Casper's childhood artwork including drawings, paintings, a molded plaster sculpture and a ceramic monogram.
Biographical / Historical
Timothy Casper (1943-1964) was a printmaker and draftsman from Milwaukee, Wisconsin whose artistic ability was recognized at a young age by artist and professor Gerald Landt, leading to Casper enrolling in special art classes at the Milwaukee Art Institute in 1953. From there Casper continued studying art throughout high school at the Putney School in Vermont, going on to start his bachelor's degree in art history at New York University in 1962. During his short life Casper managed to travel across Europe and the East Coast of the United States, visiting art museums and historical landmarks, including a fateful trip to Paris in 1964 where Casper died as a result of injuries sustained in a car accident. After his death, his mother Elise Ott Casper organized a series of memorial exhibitions across the United States as well as at the Galerie Wolfgang Gurlitt in Munich, Germany.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Bequest of Elise Ott Casper, mother of Tim Casper, in 1998.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as eight series
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1943-1966 (0.3 Linear feet Box 1, OV 5)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1943-1981 (1 Linear foot Box 1-2)
Series 3: Writings, 1953-1969 (0.2 Linear feet Box 2)
Series 4: Exhibition Files, 1965-1967 (0.2 Linear feet Box 2)
Series 5: Personal Business, 1956-1967 (0.4 Linear feet Box 2-3)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1956-1960 (0.1 Linear feet Box 3)
Series 7: Photographic Material, circa 1943-1965 (0.4 Linear feet Box 3)
Series 8: Artwork, circa 1945-1964 (0.9 Linear feet Box 3- 4, OV 6)
Draftsmen (artists) -- Wisconsin -- Milwaukee; Printmakers -- Wisconsin -- Milwaukee
- Biographical Material, 1943-1966; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1, OV 5
  Scope and Contents
  Biographical material includes Casper's birth and baptism certificates, his social security card and resumes and biographic summaries. Also included are materials related to his education such as school report cards, school merit certificates and graduation records; along with a baby book and summer camp achievement patches.
  - Birth and Baptism Certificates, 1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Social Security Card, circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Compiled Biographical Summary and Resumes, circa 1958-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Elementary School Certificates and Awards, 1955-1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Putney School Graduation Diploma, 1962; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 5, Folder 1)
  - Report Cards, 1953; 1962-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Baby Scrapbook, 1943-1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - American Red Cross and Summer Camp Achievement Patches and Certificates, circa 1953-1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1943-1981; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 1 Linear foot Box 1-2
  Correspondence contains letters from Timothy Casper to Elise Ott Casper from when he was attending the Putney boarding school in Vermont, traveling abroad and during his time at New York University. Other correspondence from Timothy Casper include post cards to Paul Reisen and holiday cards from Casper. Also found in this series are correspondence to Elise Ott Casper related to her son's career and/or life. Noteable correspondence includes dancer and family friend Gerard Willem Van Loon and the Smithsonian's National Collection of Art. Also found are holiday and birthday cards to Thomas Casper from friends and family.
  Correspondence from Timothy Casper is arranged chronologically and other correspondence to Elise Ott Casper is arranged alphabetically.
  - Letters to Elise Ott Casper from Timothy Casper, The Putney School, 1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letters to Elise Ott Casper from Timothy Casper, The Putney School, 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  - Letters to Elise Ott Casper from Timothy Casper, The Putney School, 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letters to Elise Ott Casper from Timothy Casper, The Putney School, 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letters to Elise Ott Casper from Timothy Casper, The Putney School, 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Travel Letters to Elise Ott Casper from Timothy Casper, 1960-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
  - Letters to Elise Ott Casper from Timothy Casper, New York University, 1962-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16-18)
  - Postcards from Timothy Casper to Paul Riesen, 1959-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - F, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - J, 1958; 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - L, 1955; 1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Ragnar Ness, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Walter Ott, 1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Smithsonian National Collection of Fine Art, 1965-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Gerald Willem Van Loon, 1950-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26-29)
  - Gerald Willem Van Loon, 1950-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1-6)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, Last Name Unsigned, 1954-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Holiday Cards from Timothy Casper, circa 1956-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Holiday and Birthday Cards to Timothy Casper, circa 1944-1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Writings, 1953-1969; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 2
  Writings contain writings by Timothy Casper, Elise Ott Casper and others. Writing by Timothy Casper include a diary, an eight grade essay on monoprinting, travel notes and a draft of his New York Univeristy course schedule. Writings by others include teacher feedback notes, an annotated list of Casper's artwork, writings related to the planning and publishing of a book on Timothy Casper including a introduction outline, lists of artworks to be featured and correspondence.
  - Timothy Casper Diary, 1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Eight Grade Composition on Monoprints, 1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - The Putney School Teacher Feedback Notes, 1958-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - New York University Class Schedule Outline, 1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Travel Notes, circa 1959-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Annotated List of Artwork, circa 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Artwork Notes, circa 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Timothy Casper Book Planning Documents, 1966-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Exhibition Files, 1965-1967; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 2
  Exhibition files document six memorial exhibitions of Casper's work. Items include guest and address lists, agendas, writings, invoices, artwork insurance policies, correspondence and printed material.
  - Timothy Casper Memorial Exhibitions, Archival Resource Key
    - Milwaukee Art Center (Sept. 13-Oct. 3, 1965), Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - University School of Milwaukee (Apr. 4-May 15, 1966), Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - The Putney School, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Anthroposophical Society in America, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Timothy F. Casper (Apr. 13-May 8, 1967), Galerie Wolfgang, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22-23)
    - Woman's Club of Wisconsin, Milwaukee (Jan. 1966), Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Personal Business, 1956-1967; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 0.4 Linear feet Box 2-3
  Personal business records include Timothy Casper's estate papers and life insurance documentation, alphabetized artwork title cards with corresponding loan and sale information and an invoice for napkins from Casper's printing business "Casper Studios".
  - Estate Settlement and Life Insurance Records, 1958-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Artwork Loan and Sale Record Information Cards, Archival Resource Key
    - A, 1962-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - B, 1958-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - C, 1957-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - D, 1958-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - E, 1958-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - F, 1958-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - G, 1956-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - H, 1956-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - J, 1958-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - L, 1958-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - M, 1957-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - N, 1960-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - O, 1960-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - P, 1959-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - R, 1958-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - S, 1957-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - T, 1957-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - V, 1958-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - W, 1956-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Z, 1961-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Casper Studio Invoice, 1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Printed Material, 1956-1960; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 3
  Printed Material includes exhibition flyers and newspaper clippings, primarily related to Casper's memorial exhibitions; a copy of Timothy F. Casper 1943-1964, a published book on the life and career of Casper; a program for an elementary school play Casper participated in; brochures for different museums; New York University Graduate School bulletin publications; postcards from different locations in Washington D.C and miscellanea.
  - Timothy F. Casper 1943-1964, Retrospective Book Published by Moebius Printing Company, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Timothy Casper Exhibition Flyers, 1965-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1959-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - 5 With Fear, Elementary School Play Program, 1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - New York University Graduate School of Art and Science Bulletins, 1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Museum Brochures, circa 1959-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Blank Postcards from Trip to Washington D.C., circa 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, circa 1957-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Photographic Material, circa 1943-1965; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; 0.4 Linear feet Box 3
  Photographic material contains portraits of Timothy Casper as a child as well as photographs of his artwork. Also found are three family photo albums of the Caspers, their family and various places they visited, along with a photo album of Casper attending Woodcraft summer camp.
  - Photographs of Artwork, 1955-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 16-17)
  - Timothy Casper Portraits, circa 1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Family Photograph Album, circa 1943-1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Family Photograph Album, circa 1944-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Some language in the captions of this album may be offensive to viewers. It is presented as it exists in the original documents for the benefit of research. This material in no way reflects the views of the Archives of American Art or the Smithsonian Institution.
  - Family Photograph Album, circa 1950-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Woodscraft Summer Camp Photograph Album, 1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Artwork, circa 1945-1964; Series 8; Archival Resource Key; 0.8 Linear feet Box 3- 4, OV 6
  Artwork consists of seven sketchbooks, loose and matted sketches, paintings, etching and linocut prints, a woven basket and bracelets. Also found is an extensive amount of Timothy Casper's childhood artwork including drawings, paintings, a molded plaster sculpture and a ceramic monogram.
  - Sketchbooks, 1963-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 23-26)
  - Sketches, circa 1958-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Matted Sketches, 1961-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 28-29)
  - Etching and Linocut Prints, circa 1953-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Matted Etchings and Linocut Prints, 1956-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 31-32)
  - Paintings, 1961-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Childhood Drawings and Paintings, circa 1948-1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Childhood Drawings and Paintings, circa 1948-1956; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 6)
  - Childhood Sculptural Art, circa 1953-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
  - Hillsboro Woven Straw Dish and Bracelets, circa 1945-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 4)